Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Attending

Manchester: Carole, Franck, Jits, Khalid, Wang

EBI: Hamish, Rodrigo

Apologies

Thomas (holiday until Thursday)

Eric (sick)

Katy( at University research day)

Minuting

Franck

Agenda

Agree on what to show at ISMB

Khalid's work on workflow and web services - can be useful for biocatalogue

Using Open Search for the biocatalogue API - short term or longer term?

Dates for the face 2 face meeting at EBI

Biocatalogue position paper for 2008 Microsoft eScience Workshop - deadline

Khalid's work on workflow and web services

Actions from Previous Meeting

Carole → Resend paper to mailing list

Eric → Send db schema to mailing list

Eric/Thoman → Investigate Passenger and Ruby Enterprise Edition for BioCatalogue pilot

Eric/Jiten/Thomas → Come up with a technical road map for the BioCatalogue project

Rodrigo → Provide access to the EBI ticketing system to BioCatalogue team in Manchester

Thomas → Setup BioCatalogue wiki and circulate link on the mailing list

Rodrigo & Thomas → Provide content for the BioCatalogue home page

Round-table

Upcoming Meetings

Carole, Katy, Jits, Thomas, Hamish & Rodrigo going to ISMB meeting (20-23 July)

Carole and Katy doing paper for the project kick-off meeting for our sysmo-db project

Jits, will be at BOSC 18-19 July

Any Other Business (AOB)

Individual password for the new wiki- is that possible?

old wiki?

AOB

Minutes

Agenda item

Agree on what to show at ISMB

We agreed that it isn't really a demo just a requirement gathering exercise. Franck will prepare of questionnaire of 10 questions maxi. It's not for distribution but will be used as a guideline when talking to people.

Using Open Search for the biocatalogue API - short term or longer term?

We'll use it for the pilot…General agreement

Dates for the face 2 face meeting at EBI

Rodrigo to send the dates EBI team is available

Biocatalogue position paper for 2008 Microsoft eScience Workshop - deadline

Khalid will help the manchester team to write the paper.

Khalid's work on workflow and web services - can be useful for biocatalogue

Khalid built a tool called “QASAR” which checks the quality of semantically annotated web services. He will send further documentation on the mailing list.

New actions

Carole - To speak to Steve petefer about the pilot

Carole/Rodrigo - Schedule an advisery meeting

Rodrigo - To send dates EBI team is available for a Face 2 face meeting

Franck - prepare a questionnaire for ISMB

Khalid - To send more info about 'QASAR' on the mailing list.

AOB

'Packs' have gone live in myExperiment !!! They can be used to group together description, web services etc. Might be useful in a service curation environment.

NB: We didn't have time to run through all the action items in the agenda

Previous/Next Minutes

Previous meeting: PhoneMeeting_24_06_2008 

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jul 15 2008

Meeting Agenda/Minutes

Date: Tuesday 14th October 2008

Time: 15:00-17:00 (UK)

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Jits, Carole

EBI: Eric, Thomas, Hamish

Apologies

Rodrigo

Minuting

Eric

Agenda

Action from the last telcon.

Progress with the pilot - are we rolling?

BioMoby web services

Annual Report (Carole)

AOB.

Actions from Previous Meeting

Jits: Speak to Dave about the new privacy policy in myExperiment

Jits: circulate myExp draft T&C's and privacy policy.

Franck (with devs): put together feature list for pilot, for end users.

Eric & Thomas: set up pilot.biocatalogue.org and deploy the current work on the pilot.

Minutes

Jits spoke to Dave about myExperiment privacy policy. Though one has been written it has not been in use so could not be circulated. The EBI terms of use are available as a basis for writing the BioCatalogue terms of use

On progress on pilot development

functionality available for user registration and management

on-going work on service submission and management, with emphasis on soap services

event logging plugin being done for my experiment that will be used for BioCatalogue as well

On release strategy for the pilot

soft and silent release at the end of October to a small community

open beta release at the end of November( beginning of December)

organize user experience/show and tell activities during November to feed into beta release for December

use press release, blogs(Duncan) and possibly bbsrc announcement as publicity channels

New Actions

Action Thomas : Create a public space on BioCatalogue wiki

Action Eric, Jits, Thomas, Franck : Establish the list of features for the pilot and road map for future development

Action Thomas : Configure the mailer on the BioCatalogue beta site

Action Eric : Investigate Biomoby script from Eddie

Action Carole : Complete Annual Report

Action Robert : Organize the advisory board meeting. Could be at EBI or Manchester and would be desirable for the whole team to be there.

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Oct 7 2008

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Oct 28 2008

v1.1.0 Release (Sep 2011)

This will be a major release with some new features and major improvements.

This will include:

New “examples” tab for services. Surfaces all existing example data and scripts for a service, and provides simple abilities to add examples.

Richer annotation values support. This will improve semantic annotation capabilities and improve performance in certain areas (like generating tag filters in the Taverna plugin).

Support for custom monitoring of REST services - maintainer of the service can provide a custom URL to monitor (which can include secret info like an API key).

(possibly) Secure web pages - site will run with SSL turned on for all pages.

Users can now see the list of people who have been granted responsibility for a service.

Some UI and performance tweaks.

IMPORTANT: this releases includes a major change in the way annotations work and thus requires a big data migration of all the Annotations data. When running "rake db:migrate" this could take over 3 hours to complete, and it's important to check the output of this to make sure everything ran OK.

Update instructions (for local and Manchester servers):

NOTE: when running in production environments make sure to set/add RAILS_ENV=production to any ruby/rake commands below.

Run:

svn update
rake db:migrate
rake db:test:prepare RAILS_ENV=test
ruby script/biocatalogue/migrate_display_names_jul11.rb
  Expected output (something like):
  > 1184 display names moved to the parent Service
  > 0 display_name annotations remaining in the db
ruby script/biocatalogue/fix_url_monitors_using_annotations_sep11.rb
  Expected output (something like):
  > 43 URL monitors updated

You may need to reindex your search index if you experience problems - rake solr solr:reindex, but note that it will take a long time to run.

Additionally, for production environments:

rake asset:packager:build_all RAILS_ENV=production

To restart an app deployed under apache and phusion passenger:

touch tmp/restart.txt

Update instructions (for EBI servers):

First, follow instructions here: http://www.biocatalogue.org/docs/installing-new-release

Note: it's CRUCIAL that the full output of the update script is viewed to ensure the migration went ahead smoothly.

Then run the following (in the directory where the code is deployed):

ruby script/biocatalogue/migrate_display_names_jul11.rb
ruby script/biocatalogue/fix_url_monitors_using_annotations_sep11.rb
rake asset:packager:build_all RAILS_ENV=production
touch tmp/restart.txt

Testing

Run the Rails tests:

rake test:units RAILS_ENV=test
rake test:functionals RAILS_ENV=test
rake test:integration RAILS_ENV=test

Run API tests

Use the DRAMA procedure to test the system

The BioCatalogue Partners & Friends

The following projects and consortia are actively collaborating with the BioCatalogue project:

EU EMBRACE network: The main objective of the EMBRACE Network of Excellence project is to integrate major databases and software tools in bioinformatics using existing integrating technologies and methods, and grid services (http://www.embracegrid.org). The deliverables of this project include a services registry (http://www.embraceregistry.net), which is aimed at helping users locate services and tools developed by the partners. The BioCatalogue and the EMBRACE registry will merge.

myExperiment (http://www.myexperiment.org) is a popular, JISC-funded, Virtual Research Environment focusing on scientific social networking, social content-sourcing and social curation for scientific workflows and other, increasingly, scientific protocols. The project is a joint venture between the Universities of Manchester (Carole Goble) and Southampton (David De Roure). myExperiment is the inspiration behind the social networking and community curation/crowd-sourcing aspects of BioCatalogue. Jiten Bhagat was a core developer on myExperiment. Both projects use the same programming environment (Ruby on Rails). The two projects are coupled; not only sharing know-how, code and architectural designs but also coupling the two resources. myExperiment will provide an alternative view of the catalogue as a service tab in its own interface, source service information from the BioCatalogue and will provide data on service co-use patterns, usage and other operational and social standing metrics through its monitoring and analysis of workflows that use the services.

OMII-UK (http://www.omii.ac.uk) and SIGENAE (http://www.sigenae.org/) have produced service monitoring software that reports on the operation of services and/or changes to the services behaviour and interfaces. In phase two we will incorporate third party reports and aggregate feeds for operational metrics (down times, reliability, quality of service etc).

myGrid (http://www.mygrid.org.uk) is the umbrella project for the development of the Taverna Workflow Workbench. BioCatalogue will be integrated into the Taverna workbench in place of the current Feta discovery component.

BioMOBY Central (http://biomoby.org) is a registry of BioMOBY services that we will cross link to. We are participating in the BioMOBY service annotation jamboree (November 2008), which has already provided a useful source of requirements for the curator workbench. Mark Wilkinson, Director of BioMOBY, serves on our SAB.

EU BioSapiens network: (http://www.biosapiens.info). The main objective of the BioSapiens Network of Excellence is to provide a large scale, concerted effort to annotate genomic data in laboratories distributed throughout Europe. Most of the services developed under this mandate consist of DAS (Distributed Annotation System) servers, very similar in implementation to traditional SOAP and REST Web services. These services are typically used to exchange biological annotations and are available via a central repository server. As some of these services are available via SOAP/REST interfaces, BioCatalogue is aiming at harvesting these in addition to exploring methodologies for making DAS server functionality generally available to the user community.

NBIC (http://www.nbic.nl/) initiates and coordinates research, education and support activities to stimulate the development of the field of bioinformatics in the Netherlands. NBIC members are playing a major role as users for BioCatalogue. Prof dr van Kampen, Director, sits on our SAB.

SeekDa (http://www.seekda.com) provides a web service search engine whose mission is to facilitate discovery and on-demand use of services over the Web. The services accessible through SeekDa site are publicly available web services. SeekDa have verbally agreed to enable BioCatalogue to source services from their site via an API. Dr Lausen, CTO of SeekDa, sits on our SAB.

International Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology in Warsaw. We have collaborated with Jerzy Orlowski and Janusz M. Bujnicki from the Laboratory of Bioinformatics and Protein Engineering, Warsaw, Poland.

EMORY University (http://www.emory.edu/home/index.html) is using and further developing the BioCatalogue software as part of the EdUnify project (registry: https://www.edunify.pesc.org/) and have also written an iPhone app.

The National Cancer Research Institute (NCRI) (http://www.ncri.org.uk/) have worked with us to add the BioCatalogue as one of the searchable resources in the ONIX portal.

Wei Tan and Jia Zhang have produced a number of award winning publications referencing the BioCatalogue and are in collaboration with us. See the publications page for more info.

BioGPS (http://biogps.org). We have some ongoing collaborations with the BioGPS with some exciting ideas for integration. Watch this space!

Rob Procter from the Manchester eResearch Centre.

Jonathon Foster

Telcon Meeting on June 03, 2008

Agenda

Attendees

Manchester - Franck, Katy, Jits

EBI - Thomas, Hamish, Eric

Apologies

Manchester - Carole

EBI - Rodrigo

Minuting

Franck

Discussions

Actions Items from Previous Meeting

EBI - Register domain name “biocatalogue.org” and contact the Korean institute about “biocatalog.org” Not sure if Rodrigo contacted the Korean

Eric/Hamish/Thomas - Join the myexperiment skype chats Done

Eric/Franck - Produce matrix of service types against bioinformatics domain coverage and properties, to generate a representative set of services to pilot with. Done

Everybody - Dump all possible attributes/information that could be collected about services on to the mailing list in order to help Eric/Franck enhance the proposed curation model. Done

Jiten/Eric/Thomas - Setup a myExperiment environment at EBI and walk through myExperiment codebase. Done

Everyone - Decide the exact date of the next telecom meeting; preferably week starting the 26/05. next meeting on Tuesday 10/06

Franck - select representative KEGG services to use. Done

Franck - send out definition of “semantic type” to mailing list for further discussion and refinement. Done, definition is in the model

Eric/Franck - work on the metatada levels for bronze/silver/gold/platinum compliance. Done, model is on the wiki

Round Table

Franck: worked on the platinum annotation model from which they've derived the bronze, silver and gold.

These models are on the wiki. Selected a number of broadly used bioinformatics web services. will now describe selected services using the model.

Jits: help Thomas and Eric to set up myexperiment code base at EBI. will meet Thomas and Eric to discuss the code base

Katy: Attending a Web service metadata meeting in Australia, the report of the meeting is on the list and the wiki.

discuss the annotation model with Franck

Eric: worked on the annotation model, Familiarising himself with myExperiment code base. Joined myExperiment 5pm chat.

Will look at the back end database.

Thomas: Set up a private myExperiment code base at EBI. Joined myExperiment 5pm chat.

Hamish: Encouraging service providers to describe their services.

Action Items

Everybody: read the services matrix and check out the annotations models

Franck: post on the list example of stories

Thomas: start advertising biocatalogue on the new domain

Others

We all agree to have at this stage weekly meeting. The next one is next Tuesday 3-5pm

Everybody should start writing 'stories' about what they do

Franck: looking for example of services with security/licensing/restrictions issues to use as example.

Biocatalogue back end: Ruby on Rails or Java? Jits said Java would be better.

Date: Wednesday 03rd February 2010

Time: 15:00-16:00 (UK)

Telcon No: 08444737630

Pin: 70503011

Attending

Manchester: Franck, Jits, Manni

EBI: Eric, Rodrigo

Apologies

Minuting

Agenda

Actions from the last telecom [SAB]

Progress report

Paper progress

Service execution

Publicity/outreach

Technical meeting

Summary of tasks on Rubyforge

BioCatalogue support review

20 Questions analysis

Actions from Previous Meeting

Actions from SAB meeting

(Jits) To send to Mark detailed information on the APIs

(All) Ensure that focus is placed on web2.0 aspects to demonstrate the utility of the service it provides. The APIs are keys elements to achieve that.

(SAB) To point to ontologies that can be used to provide richer annotation of services.

(Jits) To request data dump on service links in BioMoby in appropriate format.

(All) Revisit the Platinum, Gold, silver, bronze annotation model

(All) To discuss with seekda team the minimum annotation required for services

(All) revisit MIAWS (Minimum Information About Web Service)

(All) Talk to seekda about better integration between the BioCatalogue and seekda registry.

(Franck & Jonathan) BioCatalogue questionnaire to address who the BioCatalogue users are (Biologists, computer scientists, Bioinformaticians, etc)

(All) Promote features like the APIs and the service testing harness and monitoring as advantages to registering services.

(All) Continue to promote BioCatalogue as the one stop shop for bio web service

Actions last meeting

Possibility of exploring a REST modeling paper

Franck: Biological services to describe in different model: WSMO, SWASDL, FU,

Franck: Literature review for task mining

Jits/Eric: Create a developer section on the wiki

Franck: 5 key elements to bring in the community for annotation

Minutes

1. Need a content campaign - GUIDELINES.

Make annotation guideline more visible through the website

We need a developer section on the wiki

Provide WS annotation guidelines for service developers to encourage them to add annotations to WSDL.

Possible BioCatalogue day at the EBI

2. Involvement of EMBL-EBI - OTT & Developers.

EBI advertises the catalogue at most of event they attend so does Manchester

Encourage service provider to link back to the BioCatalogue from their website

ECCB submission deadline is for April

3. development of some simple curation protocols using simple tools (ties with 1).

Need to revisit the roadmap after the next updates (2-3 weeks)

Curation wizard and spreadsheet to be added to the roadmap

4-On-going work:

a. EMBRACE catalogue fully absorbed

b. monitoring and profiling stuff in place to show added value

c. API

⇒About 2-3 weeks to go to complete all this work

New actions

Carole to send Rodrigo NAR papers reviewers

Eric/Franck make sure the annotation best practice is more visible on the site.

Franck to ask service provider to link back to the catalogue

Jits to send initial draft

Upcoming Meetings

AOB

JIRA will be used for bug tracking

Previous/Next Meetings

Previous meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Jan 25 2010

Next meeting: Phone Conference Meeting on Feb 18 2010